Lorenzo Fabbri

Summary

I am a PhD student at the Barcelona Institute for Global Health (ISGlobal). I work under the supervision of Prof. Martine Vrijheid. My main topic of interest is the use of modern Causal Inference methods to answer questions in the broad field of Environmental Neuroepidemiology. I am also profoundly interested in Open Science and Reproducible Research.

I received my Bachelor's degree in Biotechnology and my Master's degree in Quantitative and Computational Biology. My personal webpage can be found here. You can also find me on Bluesky and GitHub.

Working Experience

working Experience		
PhD Student		
Barcelona Institute for Global Health (Barcelona, ES)	2021 - Present	
Student Research Assistant Fellowship		
Università della Svizzera italiana (Lugano, CH)	2017 - 2017	
Research Visits		
Visiting PhD Student		
Harvard Pilgrim Health Care (Boston, US)	2024 - 2024	
Funding		
Causal Inference for Environmental Mixtures		
Società Unione Mutuo Soccorso (San Marino, SM)	2024	
Causal Inference for Environmental Mixtures		
ATHLETE (Barcelona, ES)	2024	
Causal Inference for Environmental Mixtures		
Centro de Investigación Biomédica en Red (Madrid, ES)	2024	
Meritatamente 2022		
Società Unione Mutuo Soccorso (San Marino, SM)	2022	
Erasmus+ Traineeship Programme Scholarship		
University of Trento (Trento, IT)	2019	
Faculty of Informatics Scholarship		
Università della Svizzera italiana (Lugano, CH)	2016	
Erasmus Traineeship Programme Scholarship		
University of Parma (Parma, IT)	2015	
Honors and Awards		
Outstanding Abstract by a Student International Society for Environmental Epidemiology	2022	
Publications		
My ORCiD is 0000-0003-3031-322X.		

1. **Fabbri L**, Garlantézec R, Audouze K, et al. Childhood exposure to non-persistent endocrine disrupting chemicals and multi-omic profiles: A panel study. *Environment International*. Published online February 26, 2023:107856. doi:10.1016/j.envint.2023.107856

Journal Articles

2. Thiel C, Cordes H, **Fabbri L**, et al. A Comparative Analysis of Drug-Induced Hepatotoxicity in Clinically Relevant Situations. *PLOS Computational Biology*. 2017;13(2):e1005280. doi:10.1371/journal.pcbi.1005280

Articles under review and revising

- 1. Childhood exposure to non-persistent endocrine disruptors, glucocorticosteroids, and attentional function: A study based on the parametric g-formula. First author
- 2. Multi-omics architecture of obesity and metabolic dysfunction in childhood: identifying biological pathways and prenatal determinants. Co-author
- 3. Diet among European children and its association with adiposity-related outcomes: a multi-country study. Co-author

Software Packages

myphd: R package for "my" PhD.

https://github.com/isglobal-cep/myphd

2024

Conference Presentations

The posters can be found here.

Childhood exposure to non-persistent endocrine disrupting chemicals and multi-omic profiles: a panel study

ISEE Annual Conference, Athens (GR)

2022

Childhood exposure to non-persistent endocrine disrupting chemicals and multi-omic markers in a population-based child cohort

EURION Cluster Annual Meeting (online)

2022

Childhood exposure to non-persistent endocrine disrupting chemicals and multi-omic markers in a population-based child cohort

International Prenatal Programing and Toxicity Meeting (online)

2022

Efficient and Portable MPI Support for Approximate Bayesian Computation

Platform for Advanced Scientific Computing Conference, Lugano (CH)

2017

Education

Postgraduate Diploma in Global Health Policy

London School of Hygiene and Tropical Medicine (London, GB)

2024 - Present

Graduate Certificate in Theoretical Statistics and Probability

The Open University (Milton Keynes, GB)

2024 - Present

PhD Programme in Biomedicine

Universitat Pompeu Fabra (Barcelona, ES)

2021 - Present

- Supervisor: Prof. Martine Vrijheid.

M.Sc. in Quantitative and Computational Biology

Università degli Studi di Trento (Trento, IT)

2017 - 2019

- Thesis (FBK, Trento (IT)): Machine Learning for Predictive Drug Induced Hepatotoxicity. Supervised by: Dr. Cesare Furlanello, Dr. Marco Chierici, Prof. Enrico Domenici.
- Internship (HITS, Heidelberg (DE)): Machine and Deep Learning for Predictive Unbinding Kinetics of Kinases. Supervised by: Prof. Rebecca Wade, Dr. Daria Kokh, Prof. Raffaello Potestio.
- Final mark: 110/110 With Honors.

M.Sc. Student in Computational Science

Università della Svizzera italiana (Lugano, CH)

2016 - 2017

- Project (USI, Lugano (CH)): Investigation by Computational Techniques of Channelopaties related to Sodium Channels. Supervised by: Prof. Vittorio Limongelli, Prof. Daniele Di Marino.

B.Sc. in Biotechnology

University of Parma (Parma, IT)

2012 - 2016

- Thesis (RWTH, Aachen (DE)): Whole Body PBPK Modeling of Valproic Acid. Supervised by: Prof. Elena Maestri, Prof. Lars M. Blank, Dr. Henrik Cordes.
- Final mark: 103/110.

Continuing Education

Spring School in Causal Inference with Observational Data Causal Insights, Leeds (UK)	Apr 2022	
Computational Bayesian methods using brms in R Physalia Courses, online	Feb 2022	
ELIXIR Omics Integration and Systems Biology National Bioinformatics Infrastructure Sweden, online	Sep 2021	
Fundamentals of Epidemiology (EPM101) LSHTM, online	Sep 2021	
Advanced Statistics: Statistical Modelling Swiss Institute of Bioinformatics, online	Aug 2021	
Alpine Exposome Summer School Inserm and ATHLETE, online	Jun 2021	
Metabolomics Data Processing and Data Analysis University of Birmingham, online	Feb 2021	
Mendelian Randomisation Imperial College London, online	May 2020	
Image Analysis and Modeling of Complex Biological Dynamics University of Wurzburg, Wurzburg (DE)	Sep 2017	
Effective High Performance Computing Summer School CSCS and University of Lugano, Lugano (CH)	Jul 2017	
MARVEL School on Variationally Enhanced Sampling University of Lugano, Lugano (CH)	Feb 2017	
Advanced Course in Alternatives to Animal Experimentation University of Genova, Genoa (IT)	Nov 2015	
Service		
Students and New Researchers Network International Society for Environmental Epidemiology	2022 - 2023	
Early Career Scientist Working Group COnsortium of METabolomics Studies	2022 - 2022	

Skills

Languages	Italian (native), English (C1, IELTS 7.0), Spanish (basic)
Programming Languages	R, Python, MATLAB, C
Markup Languages	LaTeX, RMarkdown
Software Development	git, SLURM, High Performance Scientific Computing